# 澳门
Macau
# 来澳门 我们还没有尝试这边的早饭
We haven't tried the breakfast of Macau
# 今天早上呢 咱们将要前往前面的巷子
So this morning, we are gonna go to the little alley over there
# 喝一碗粥
to try a bowl of congee
# 这家粥店别看地方不大
This congee shop looks small
# 只是在一个几米的走廊里
Located in a narrow alley that's only a few meters deep
# 它狭窄到什么程度呢 就是
How narrow it is? It's like
# 除了老板之外 只能走一个人
Apart from the chef, it only allows one person to go through
# 但是 人真的很多
Nevertheless, there are quite a lot people here
# 走过了
I almost passed by without noticing it
# 是这个
It's here!
# 如果我刚才没有留意到
If I didn't see it
# 今天早上 我可能连饭都吃不着了
I would probably miss my breakfast this morning
# 别说 如此隐蔽的早餐摊
Believe it or not, such a hidden breakfast place
# 里面喝粥的人
the number of guests inside
# 竟然要比外面马路上的人都要多
are even more than those on the street
# 门口呢 还堵着一群想要进去的人
The entrance is crowded with customers who want to squeeze in
# 这边卖的生滚粥 种类并没有很稀奇
The congee sold here is not uncommon
# 像我们以前经常能够看到的猪杂 鱼片 肉丸
using ingredients that we often see - pork offal, fish slices, meatballs
# 这边都有
They have them all here.
# 想好了自己要点哪种粥
After you have decided what kind of congee you wanna have
# 老板会现场给你抓食材
The chef will gather the ingredients in front of you
# 放在锅里 和白粥煮一会儿
Put them in the pot and boil with the rice congee
# 几分钟吧 就可以上桌了
In about a few minutes, it will be ready to serve
# 但是 做的再快
Nevertheless, no matter how fast they can cook the congee
# 饭点的时候 也赶不上顾客点的速度
During breakfast, they cannot keep up with the customers' orderings.
# 于是 我们决定 打包带走
So we decide to order take out
# 鱼片粥
Fish slice congee
# 25块钱
25 yuan
# 这个是我们买的25块钱的鱼片粥
This is what we ordered, 25-yuan fish slice congee
# 加了一个7块钱的油条
with a 7-yuan You Tiao (deep-fried dough stick)
# 因为里面的人实在是太多了
Because too many people are in there
# 根本没地方坐
We have no place to sit
# 所以呢 我们就是打包出来吃
So we take them outside to eat
# 想不到这么狭窄的档口
I never knew that such a narrow place
# 生意是真好
Can have such a reputation
# 这个粥看上去就很美味
You feel it tastes good just by looking at it.
# 白白糯糯的米粥 加上诱人的鱼片
White and tender rice congee with delicious fish slices
# 中间撒了姜丝还有香葱
seasoned by ginger shreds and scallions
# 我们迫不及待尝一口吧
I can't wait to have a taste
# 咸鲜度正好
The salt and umami taste just right
# 其中的大米
The rice in the congee
# 几乎快融化成水了
almost melts into the water
# 舀一勺 流下去
Take a spoonful of congee it flows away
# 米都是这种粘稠的状态
The rice is all of such sticky and fluid texture
# 熬的已经化了
It's been cooked to melted
# 我们是从上面 翻着朝下喝
We start from the surface
# 上面有米油 还有鱼油
with the fat from rice and fish
# 吃起来特别香
The aroma is strong
# 使劲翻呢 还能看到鱼片 大块的鱼片
Dig deep down and turn it up, you can see large slices of fish
# 从下面 涌上来
emerging from the bottom
# 一碗热粥下肚
A bowl of warm congee ends up in my stomach
# 我们又继续穿梭在澳门的大街小巷
We go on shuttling on the streets of Macau
# 随人群买了一杯瓦煲咖啡
Imitating others, I bought a cup of coffee brewed with clay pot
# 我忘了 我要的是烫的
I forget it! I've asked for a hot one
# 又垂涎别人手上的蛋挞
What's more, I drooled over the egg tarts they had
# 吃一口就是有鸡蛋香甜的味道
Have a bite, and the aromatic and sweet taste of eggs comes out
# 而且还有淡淡的奶油的味道
Together with a light taste of cream
# 一个个门面不大的小吃店 总是排起长队
Those snack shops do not have a conspicuous facade, but are always crowded with a long queue
# 我不禁叹了一声
Can't help to sighhhh
# 吃点好吃的 好难
It's so hard to taste some good stuff
# 广东·中山
Zhongshan, Guangdong Province
# 时隔一年
After a year
# 我又出现在了广东的早茶点
I come to Guangdong's morning tea restaurant again
# 这次 咱们吃早茶的地方
This time we are gonna have morning tea
# 就是后面这家看起来很像大排档的店
at this place behind me - it looks like an open-air food stall
# 怎么说呢 从外面看
How to describe it? You see from the outside
# （店）几乎看不到任何的装修
you barely see any decoration
# 就是很多人 围坐在一起
Just plenty of people sitting around together
# 喝着茶 吃着点心
drinking tea and having dim sum
# 外面已经坐了十几桌
There're over 10 tables of guests out there
# 我们进去看一看 里面是什么样子吧
Let's go in and see what it's like inside.
# 这家店 别看门脸不大
This restaurant don't have a large facade
# 走进来就像进入了花果山一样
but when you go inside, it's like going into a completely different world.
# 地方特别大 桌子特别多
The place is extremely spacious with lots of tables
# 而且感觉每一桌 都是在吃酒席一样
and it seems that the guests at each table are having a pleasant banquet.
# 我们到里面去看一下
Let's go further inside
# 哦 这里面还有
Oh, they've got more in here
# 我觉得这边 上百桌是有的
I think there are over 100 tables
# 这只是一个吃早茶的地方
This is only a place for morning tea. *WOW!*
# 拿这个卡 到档口选东西
Take this card with you and pick what you want at the stalls
# 这个是给我们的牙签
These are the toothpicks we were given
# 这个（卡）是我们自己拿着的
This (card) we take with ourselves
# 到那边去点东西
Place our order over there. Let's go!
# 这一屉屉的小点心 别说我们认不全
These trays of dim sum, we can't tell the name of each
# 怕店里的人 也不能完全叫得上它们的名字
I'm afarid that neither can the staff know all the names
# 大哥 我想问一下 点心大约有多少种
Brother, do you know how many kinds of dim sum you have here?
# 品种有两百多 差不多三百个品种吧
Over 200, I think nearly 300 kinds
# 我们到现在已经有18年了
This place's been here for 18 years
# 点心的品种是特别多
They do have lots of different dim sum
# 但是不可能二三个品种呼呼地全摆出来
But they cannot lay out all
# 咱们现在就是看到什么
So now we are like, taking from whatever we see
# 喜欢吃什么 然后拿什么
the dim sum we'd like to eat
# 我拿个虾饺
I will have some shrimp dumplings
# 对 有牛仔骨吗
Yeah, do you have short ribs?
# 拿一笼
I will take a tray of it
# 给我卡
Hand me the card
# 那边不还有吗 我再到那边去点
There're more over there, aren't there? I will have more from that side
# 谢谢
Thanks!
# 这还有很多的点心
Here are quite a lot dim sum
# 咱们这次早茶的内容是
So what we've got for today's morning tea are
# 牛仔骨 虾饺 皮蛋瘦肉粥
Short ribs, shrimp dumplings, and pork congee with preserved eggs.
# 还要了一盘的凉菜
We also asked for a cold dish
# 因为我们不太懂茶
Because we don't really know much about tea
# 就叫阿姨随便上了一壶
We asked for a random tea from the staff
# 我也不知道是什么茶 反正品就是了
I don't know what kind of tea it is, but taste it anyway
# 你看 这边的点心都是放在小竹笼里的
You see, the dim sum here are all served in such little bamboo trays
# 像虾饺就是四个为一笼
Like the shrimp dumplings, a tray have four in it
# 拿一屉就可以了
It's just fine to take one tray
# 这个就是牛仔骨
This is the short ribs.
# 里面还是放了一个小盘子
There's still a small plate in the tray
# 能够看到牛仔骨是四五块的大骨头
As you can see, there are four to five large bones
# 里面还放了一些花生
With a little peanut
# 尝尝这边的虾饺
Let me have taste of the shrimp dumplings here
# 虾饺 就是看上去外面是透明的
The shrimp dumplings, they look transparent from the outside
# 能看到里面的馅儿
You can see the filling
# 鼓鼓囊囊的馅儿
Very abundant fillings
# 这一个虾饺下去 里面一个大虾仁就出来了（第一句有点模糊，我根据场景意译了一下）
Tear down the wrapper and a large shrimp slips out
# 吃这么一口虾仁 还是感觉很幸福的
It's indeed a bliss to have a bite of this shrimp
# 接下来我要隆重介绍
Now I'm gonna introduce
# 今天最难看的牛仔骨
Today's most bad-looking beef on the bone
# 但是也是最好吃的牛仔骨
The most delicious though
# 它虽然说 外面黑黢黢的
Although it looks pitch black
# 但它是黑椒味的
But it has the black pepper flavour
# 吃起来虽然说 有点油
It taste a little greasy
# 但是味道真的不错
But it's indeed very delicious
# 黑椒当中 还带有一点麻和辣的味道
The black pepper sauce has some spicy and numb taste
# 刚吃下去第一口就流口水了
My mouth is watering from the first bite
# 这应该是我喝过料最多的皮蛋瘦肉粥了
This should be the the most ample pork and preserved eggs congee I've ever had
# 碗大 里面的瘦肉多
A large bowl, and there're lots of lean pork in it
# 我不知道
I don't know
# 大家最常喝皮蛋瘦肉粥的地方是哪里
where you guys often have pork and preserved eggs congee
# 我是在某快餐品牌最常喝这个
I often have it at KFC
# 但是 两者真的差距很大
But there's a sharp contrast between them
# 它这里面是放了皮蛋还有肉
It has preserved eggs and pork
# 你喝一口 不仅有大米的绵软
Have a taste, you not only get the tender texture of rice
# 还有一口的香甜
and the mouthful of aroma
# 我们又闯入了老年人的天地
We break into the world of the elder again
# 现在是早茶时间
Now is the time for morning tea
# 和很多的爷爷奶奶在这边一起 吃早茶
Having morning tea here together with lots of grandpas and grandmas
# 现在已经吃完点心了
Now we've finished our dim sum
# 接下来的时光就是 倒杯茶
Next we'll spend the time on having a cup of tea
# 品味一下接下来美好的时光
And have a taste of this pleasant moment
# 同样是老太太 你看人家就在这边喝早茶
These grandmas here are having morning tea
# 我奶奶早上起来就去超市门口抢鸡蛋 哈哈
But my grandma would go to store and grab some eggs in the morning, haha